A Guide to the Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger Papers, 1970-2007
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger Papers, 1970-2007
Library of Virginia
31719, 44035, 45329
2.5 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger, Richmond, Virginia, 21 January 1983. Gift of Samuel Markel, executor of the estate of Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger, Richmond, Virginia, 7 July 2008. Gift of Sharon Nordlinger, New York, New York 1 January 2011.
Biographical Information
Zelda Kingoff was born 19 January 1932 in Greenville, South Carolina, to Joseph Kingoff and Alice Heiner Kingoff. The family moved to Richmond while she was a teenager and she attended Richmond public schools. Kingoff graduated from Marjorie Webster Junior College in 1952 and from Sally Tompkins School of Nursing in 1963. She married Martin Stanford Nordlinger (1930-2002) 24 December 1963. Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger was a lobbyist to the Virginia general assembly from 1971 to 1976, a free lance writer, and active in the women's movement. She was a co-founder of the Richmond chapter of the National Organization for Women in 1971. Nordlinger was also active in the National Women's Political Caucus and the Virginia Women's Political Caucus. Nordlinger had two children from a previous marriage and two daughters with Martin Nordlinger. Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger died 18 March 2008 in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1970-2007, of Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger (1932-2008) of Richmond, Virginia, consisting of articles, bills, biographies, campaign buttons, church bulletins, circular letters, civil actions, clippings, essays, letters, lists, newsletters, newspapers, pamphlets, press releases, questionaires, resolutions, and speeches relating to Nordlinger's activities as a member of the Women's Liberation movement and the National Organization for Women (NOW).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Personal Papers containing Correspondence, 1970-2006; Statements, Speeches, and Writings; Biographical Information; Notes; Financial papers, 1984-1989; and miscellaneous personal papers.
Series II: Suits and Complaints.
Series III: Subject files.
Series IV: Articles.
Series V: Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1937-2007.
Series VI: Magazines and Newsletters.
VII: Organization Papers.
Series VIII: Miscellaneous Papers.
Series IX: Political Campaign Buttons.
Contents List
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1970-2006., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Series I: Personal papers consist of subseries A: Correspondence, 1970-2006; subseries B: Biographical Information; subseries C: Statements, Speeches, and Writings; subseries D: Notes; subseries E: Financial Papers, 1984-1989; and subseries F: Miscellaneous Personal Papers.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1970-2006., 10 folders. (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
    Correspondence, 1970-2006, contains letters between Zelda Nordlinger and other women active in the women's rights movement at the local, state and national levels, discussing meetings, demonstrations, and other plans to advance women's rights, including her successful efforts to integrate the Thalhimer's Soup Bar in Richmond. Also includes correspondence with businesses and individuals regarding women in the workplace and sexism in educational materials. Also contains correspondence with members of the Virginia general assembly and the United States Congress urging their support for the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), and other legislation concerning women, including child care, rape, welfare, and abortion. Also includes letters to the Richmond Times-Dispatch, Playboy, and other publications concerning women's rights and issues.
    Chronological.
    - Correspondence, 1970. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1974. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1975. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1982-2006. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Biographical Information., 1 folder. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Biographical information contains information about Nordlinger written by her and others.
  - Subseries C: Statements, Speeches, and Writings., 1 folder. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Statements, Speeches, and Writings concern women's rights, the Equal Rights Amendment, abortion, the media, politics, sexism, and welfare, including stories on integrating the Thalhimer's Soup Bar and on Richmond mayor and Congressman Thomas J. Bliley.
  - Subseries D: Notes., 1 folder. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Notes consist of notes made by Nordlinger regarding women's rights, abortion, politics, as well as women and literature, religion, and psychology.
  - Subseries E: Financial Papers, 1984-1989., 1 folder. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Financial Papers, 1984-1989 consist of acounts of and copies of checks to Nordlinger from Metropolitan Communciations and the Virginian-Pilot and Ledger-Star.
  - Subseries F: Miscellaneous Personal Papers., 3 folders. (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
    Miscellaneous Personal papers consist of medical information containing information on prescriptions for Martin and Zelda Nordlinger, as well as copies of the Folstein mini-mental state examination; Meyers-Briggs Test contains results for Zelda and Martin Nordlinger; and certificate, 29 June 2003, for Zelda Nordlinger as Correspondent of the Day for the Richmond Times-Dispatch.
    - Medical information and test. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Meyers-Briggs test and results. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Certificate, 29 June 2003, to Zelda Nordlinger as Correspondent of the Day for the Richmond Times-Dispatch. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Suits and Complaints., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Suits and Complaints contains lawsuit papers against the Southwestern General Life Insurance Company and the Richmond Times-Dispatch for sex discrimination, particularly the Times-Dispatch's policy of segregating want ads into male and female, and also a complaint against the Richmond City Public Schools for sex discrimination in athletics.
  - Suits and complaints. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series III: Subject Files., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Subject files contain clippings and articles discussing the media and clippings, articles, and notes concerning feminism and militarism from the late 19th century until the present.
  - The Media, 1981, 1991-1995, and no date. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Feminism and militarism from the late 19th century to the early 20th to the present--notes and correspondence (folder 1 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Feminism and militarism from the late 19th century to the early 20th to the present--clippings, 1980-1983, (folder 2 of 4). (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Feminism and militarism from the late 19th century to the early 20th to the present--articles, 1915-1972, (folder 3 of 4). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Feminism and militarism from the late 19th century to the early 20th to the present--articles, 1976-1982, and no date (folder 4 of 4). (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Articles., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  Articles consist of journal and magazine articles, as well as book excerpts concerning women focusing on abortion, art, education, employment and labor, family relations, the feminist movement, literature, gender issues, politics, pornography, religion, reproductive issues, science, sex, and relationship between wives and husbands. Includes articles by Betty Friedan, Germaine Greer, and Shere Hite.
  - The Backlash Phenomenon by Helen B. Wolfe in Vital Speeches of the Day, June 1976. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Beyond the Feminist Mystique by Benjamin F. Barber in The New Republic, 11 July 1983. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Excerpts from The Book of Women's Achievements by Joan Macksey and Kenneth Macksey, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book review by Shelly Errington in Signs, Spring 1982. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bringing Women into the Curriculum by Dorothy J. Zuersher in Education Digest, February 1977. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Early Modern Fraternalism and the Patriarchal Family by Mary Ann Clawson in Feminist Studies vol. 6, no. 2, Summer 1980. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The End of Internationalization: Adorno's Social Psychology by Jessica Benjamin in Telos vol. 32, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ev'ry Woman is at Heart a Rake by Patricia Meyer Spacks in Eighteenth Century Studies, Fall 1974. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Family Reform Movements: Recent Feminism and Its Opposition by Susan Harding in Feminist Studies vol. 7, no. 1, Spring 1981. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Feminists and Religious Trailblazers by Dorothy Emerson and Men, Women, and Margaret Fuller by Faye Bayly in The World, March/April 1992. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - A Five Dimensional Model for Change: Contradictions and Feminist Consciousness by Berit Ås in Women's Studies International Quarterly vol. 4, no. 1, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Forum on pornography in Harper's, November 1984. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Gender and Dichotomy by Nancy Jay in Feminist Studies vol. 7, no. 1, Spring 1981. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Girl Talk Boy Talk by John Pfeiffer in Science, February 1985. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Girls in Suits at Lunch by Deanne Stillman in GQ, October 1985. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - God the Father in The Women's History of the World by Rosalind Miles, 1989. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Greek Citizen Woman in Attic Vase Painting by Amy Swerdlow in Women's Studies vol. 5, no. 3, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - How to Deal with the New Unemployment by Walter Guzzardi, Jr., in Fortune, February 1977. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - How to Get the Women's Movement Moving Again by Betty Friedan in New York Times Magazine, 3 November 1985. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Article by Joan Walsh in In These Times, 11-17 December 1985. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Interview with Candace Pert in Omni, February 1982. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Is Female to Male as Nature Is to Culture? by Sherry B. Ortner in Women, Culture, and Society, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Excerpt from The Kinsey Institute New Report on Sex. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Excerpt from Libby Holman: Body and Soul by Hamilton Darby Perry, 1983. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lilith: First Woman, First Feminist by Nella Fermi Weiner in International Journal of Women's Studies, November-December 1979. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Made for Man's Delight: Rousseau as Antifeminist by Victor G. Wexler in American Historical Review vol. 81, no. 1-3, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Monotheism and Gender Status: A Cross-Societal Study by Ronal Stover and Christine A. Hope in Social Forces, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Mother Maiden and the Marriage of Death: Women Writers and an Ancient Myth by Susan Gubar in Women's Studies vol. 6, no. 3, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Not for Women Only by Betty Friedan in Modern Maturity, April-May 1989. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - An Ounce of Prevention by the Ad Hoc Committee for Contraception and Abortion Information. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The Politics of Housework by Pat Mainardi. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - The Politics of Motherhood by Deborah Fallows in Washington Monthly, June 1985. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - The Prejudice of Parents by Ellen Mints. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Reproductive Continuity: Capturing the Magic of Maternity from The Mother Machine by Gena Corea, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Requiem for the Women's Movement by Veronica Geng in Harper's, November 1976. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Re-reading Political Theory from a Woman's Perspective by Diana Coole in Political Studies vol. XXXIV, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Review of Women in Western Political Thought by Naomi Scheman in the Philosophical Review, July 1982. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - The Sacrificial Lamb from Pornography and Silence by Susan Griffin, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Excerpt from Sexism and God-Talk by Rosemary Radford Ruether, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Excerpts from The Sisterhood: The True Story of the Women Who Changed the World by Marcia Cohen, 1988, (folder 1 of 2). (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Excerpts from The Sisterhood: The True Story of the Women Who Changed the World, 1988, (folder 2 of 2). (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - The Subversive Sperm from The Mother Machine by Gena Correa, 1985. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Taking Stock: Is America In Decline? by Peter Schmeisser in New York Times Magazine, 17 April 1988. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Excerpts from The Total Man by Stan Gooch, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - The Virgin and the State by Sherry B. Ortner in Feminist Studies vol. 4, no. 1, February 1978. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Excerpts from The War Against Women by Marilyn French, 1992. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - What Turns Women On? by Germaine Greer in Esquire, July 1973. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - When Are Interests Interesting by Virginia Sapiro and Beyond Interests in Politics by Irene Diamond and Nancy Hartsock in American Political Science Review vol. 75, no. 3, September 1981. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Why Marry?: The New Woman of 1918 by Judith L. Stephens in TJ, May 1982. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wives Who Cheat by Shere Hite in New Woman, November 1987. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Excerpts from Women v Women by Tara Roth Madden, 1987. (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Series V: Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1937-2007., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 3-4)
  Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1937-2007, contains clippings from newspapers and magazines discussing Nordlinger, the feminist movement in Richmond, NOW, the Equal Rights Amendment, and sex discrimination. Articles also concern women's issues and women's rights at the national, state and local levels. Topics covered by these clippings include education, employment, feminism, gay and lesbian rights, marriage and spousal relations, pornography, religion, sex and sexuality, women in politics, women's history, women's rights, as well as the efforts to have women admitted into the Virginia Military Institute (Lexington, Virginia) and the Citadel (Charleston, South Carolina). Includes clippings from the Richmond Times-Dispatch, the New York Times, and the Washington Post.
  Chronological
  - Clippings, 1937, 1958, 1968-1969. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1970-1973. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1974-1979, 197[-]. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1980-1983. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1984. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, January 1985. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, February-June 1985. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, November-December 1985, [no month] 1985. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, January-June 1986. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, July-December 1986, [no month] 1986. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, January-April 1987. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, May-November 1987, [no month] 1987. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1988. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, January-June 1989. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, July-December 1989, [no month] 1989. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 198[-]. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, January-April 1990. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, May-August 1990, Summer 1990. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, September-December 1990. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1991. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, January-August 1992. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, September 1992. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, October-December 1992. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, January-May 1993. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, June-August 1993. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, September-December 1993. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, January-April 1994. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, May-July 1994. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, August-December 1994, [no month] 1994. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, January, April-June 1995. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 199[-]. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1996, 1998. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 2000-2007. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, no date. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series VI: Magazines and Newsletters., Extent: 1 box. (Box 5)
  Magazines and Newsletters consist of magazines and newsletters related to the feminist movement, NOW, leftist politics, human rights, reproductive rights, and international peace organizations.
  - Bakerby's, September-October 1990. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - BusinessWeek, 24 September 1979. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Capitol List (Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee), 1 March 1978. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Coalition Report (Richmond Human Rights Coalition), January-February 1978. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Do It NOW: Monthly Action Newsletter of the National Organization for Women, 1972. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ms., 1972. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - NARAL News (National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League), 1994-1995. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NCJW Journal (National Council of Jewish Women, Fall 1992. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter of the Democratic Left, 1978-1980. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - NOW Acts, Fall 1971. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NOW What? (Richmond Chapter, NOW), July 1976. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Off Our Backs: A Women's Liberation bi-weekly, 31 December 1970. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Older Women's League newsletter, May 1987. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Options (Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights), 1978-1979, 1985. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Peace and Freedom (Women's International League for Peace and Freedom), Summer 2001. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Progress (Virginia League for Planned Parenthood), 1990-1994. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Richmond NOW newsletter, 1986-1994. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - The Spokeswoman, 15 April 1975. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - UUWF Journal (Unitarian Universalist Women's Federation), 15 October 1985. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Veteran Feminists of America newsletter, Spring 2006. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Virginia NOW Choices, 1988-1990. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Virginia Women (Virginia Council on the Status of Women), 1990. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Women (Virginia Foundation for Women), 1998. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - The Woman Activist and The Woman Activist Extra, 1973, 1989-1995. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Women in the Arts (The National Museum of Women in the Arts), Fall 1993. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Women's Liberation newsletter, 197[-]. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - WPTF Newsletter (National Council for a World Peace Tax Fund), August 1978. (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Series VII: Organization Papers., Extent: 1 box. (Box 5)
  Organization Papers contain circular letters, pamphlets, press releases, questionaires, and other printed materials from the ACLU, Coal Employment Project, Emily's List, the Feminist Majority Foundation, NOW, Planned Parenthood, Richmond Coalition for Choice, Richmond Human Rights Coalition, the Virginia Commission on the Status of Women, Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council, Virginia Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, the Virginia Women's Political Caucus, the Woman Activist, and the Women's Resource Center. Collection also contains a bulletin from a pro-choice service at the First Unitarian Church (Richmond, Virginia).
  - ACLU, 1970-1995. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - American Association of University Women, [1994]. (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Coal Employment Project, 1987. (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Emily's List, 1993. (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - The Feminist Majority Foundation, no date. (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - First Unitarian Church (Richmond, Virginia) bulletin, 12 May 1985. (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - NOW miscellaneous papers, 1970-1973. (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - NOW miscellaneous papers, 1989-2007, no date. (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - NOW--Virginia state chapter and Richmond chapter, 1974-1991, no date. (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Planned Parenthood, no date. (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Richmond Coalition for Choice, 1994. (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Richmond Human Rights Coalition--Human Rights Day Dinner, 10 December 1988. (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Virginia Commission on the Status of Women, no date. (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Virginia Equal Rights Amendment Ratification Council, 1984-1994. (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Virginia Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights bulletin, 21 January 1983. (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Virginia Women's Political Caucus, no date. (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - The Woman Activist, no date. (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Women's Resource Center/Women's Resource Line, 1994, no date. (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Women's Rights of Richmond, 1972[?]. (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous Papers., Extent: 1 box. (Box 6)
  Miscellaneous Papers include copies of legislative bills and resolutions concerning possible legislation on women's issues; brochures on conferences for women's issues and studies, employment and business, education, prisons, and Cuba; brochures on women's programs at the University of Richmond and at Wellesley College; book catalogs and order forms; miscellaneous papers concerning women, politics, insurance, and self defense; EBay auction information for the July 1972 issue of Ms. Magazine; list of women activists in the Richmond area; ads for Seagram's wine coolers and for bondage and domination equipment and videos; an i.q. test; miscellaneous printed materials containing anecdotes and fliers concerning women's issues; bumber stickers that say "Crater;" and business and calling cards.
  - Printed bills and legislation--rape and child custody, 1973, 1973-1994, no date. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, exhibits, lectures, 1977-2006. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Women's programs--education. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Book order forms and book catalogs. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous political and women's issues material. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Ads for wine coolers and for bondage and domination materials. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Information concerning EBay auction for issue 1 of Ms. magazine, May 2001. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Business and joke cards. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - List of women activists in the Richmond area. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Bumper stickers--Crater. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - I.Q. test booklet (2 copies). (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Series IX: Political Campaign Buttons., Extent: 1 Frame.
  Political Campaign Buttons contain political campaign buttons from the late 1960s to the 1990s for political campaigns at the state and national levels. Also contains buttons advocating various causes.